It was an afternoon in the fall of 2005.
كان بعد ظهر يوم ما في خريف 2005.
I was working at the ACLU as the organization's science advisor.
كنت أعمل في ACLU (إتحاد الحرية المدنية الأمريكي) كمستشارة المنظمة للعلوم.
I really, really loved my job,
أنا فعلا فعلا أحببت عملي ،
but I was having one of those days
لكني كنت أمر بواحدة من تلك الأيام
where I was feeling just a little bit discouraged.
التي كنت أشعر فيها ببعض من الإحباط.
So I wandered down the hallway to my colleague Chris Hansen's office.
لذلك تجولت عبر الممر إلى مكتب زميلي كريس هانسن.
Chris had been at the ACLU for more than 30 years,
كريس عمل في المنظمة لمدة تزيد عن 30 سنة ،
so he had deep institutional knowledge and insights.
لذلك هو يمتلك أفكار و معارف مؤسسية عميقة.
I explained to Chris that I was feeling a little bit stuck.
أوضحت لكريس أنني أشعر بأنني عالقة بعض الشيء.
I had been investigating a number of issues
كنت أحقق في عدد من القضايا
at the intersection of science and civil liberties -- super interesting.
ما بين العلم و الحرية المدنية - جدا مثيرة للإهتمام.
But I wanted the ACLU to engage these issues in a much bigger way,
لكني أردت المنظمة أن تشارك في هذه القضايا بطريقة أكبر ،
in a way that could really make a difference.
بطريقة من الممكن فعلا أن تحدث فارقا.
So Chris cut right to the chase, and he says,
لذلك دخل كرس في صلب الموضوع و قال:
"Well, of all the issues you've been looking at, what are the top five?"
"حسنا ، من بين جميع المشكلات التي كنت تحققين فيها ، ما هي أهم خمسة ؟"
"Well, there's genetic discrimination,
"حسنا ، هناك التمييز الجيني
and reproductive technologies,
و تقنيات الإنجاب
and biobanking, and ...
و البنوك الحيوية و ...
oh, there's this really cool issue,
أوه ، هناك ذلك الأمر الرائع جدا
functional MRI and using it for lie detection, and ...
التصوير بالرنين المغناطيسي و استخدامه لكشف الكذب و ...
oh, and of course, there's gene patents."
أوه ، و بالطبع هناك إختراع الجينات.
"Gene patents?"
"إختراع الجينات ؟"
"Yes, you know, patents on human genes."
نعم ، أتعلم ، إختراعات على الجينات البشرية.
"No!
"لا
You're telling me that the US government
أنت تقولين لي أن الحكومة الأمريكية
has been issuing patents on part of the human body?
تصدر براءات إختراع على أجزاء من الجسم البشري ؟
That can't be right."
هذا لا يمكن أن يكون صحيحا"
I went back to my office and sent Chris three articles.
عدت إلى مكتبي و أرسلت لكريس ثلاثة مقالات.
And 20 minutes later, he came bursting in my office.
وبعد 20 دقيقة عاد منفعلا إلى مكتبي
"Oh my god! You're right! Who can we sue?"
يا للهول! أنت على حق! من علينا أن نقاضي؟
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
Now Chris is a really brilliant lawyer,
في الحقيقة كريس حقا محامي رائع
but he knew almost nothing about patent law
لكن هو تقريبا لا يعلم شيء حول أنظمة براءات الإختراع
and certainly nothing about genetics.
و بالتأكيد لا شيء حول علم الوراِثة
I knew something about genetics, but I wasn't even a lawyer,
لقد كنت أعلم بعض الشيء عن علم الوراثة ، لكن لم أكن حتى محامية
let alone a patent lawyer.
لكم أن تتخيلوا محامية براءة اختراع
So clearly we had a lot to learn before we could file a lawsuit.
لذلك كان علينا أن نتعلم الكثير قبل أن نتمكن من رفع دعوى قضائية
First, we needed to understand exactly what was patented
في البداية احتجنا إلى أن نفهم بالضبط ما هي براءة الإختراع
when someone patented a gene.
عندما يقوم شخص بإختراع جين.
Gene patents typically contain dozens of claims,
إختراع الجينات عادة يحتوي على عشرات المطالبات
but the most controversial of these are to so-called "isolated DNA" --
لكن الأكثر إثارة للجدل من هذه هو ما يسمى بـ "عزل الحمض النووي"
namely, a piece of DNA that has been removed from a cell.
وهي قطعة من الحمض النووي تتم إزالتها من الخلية
Gene patent proponents say,
و يقول مؤيدو إختراع الجينات
"See? We didn't patent the gene in your body,
انظر؟ نحن لم نخترع الجينات في جسمك
we patented an isolated gene."
نحن إخترعنا جينات معزولة
And that's true,
و هذا صحيح
but the problem is that any use of the gene requires that it be isolated.
لكن المشكلة هي أنه في حالة استخدام الجينات يتطلب ذلك أن تكون معزولة
And the patents weren't just to a particular gene that they isolated,
و لم تمنح براءة الاختراع لجين معزول معين فقط
but on every possible version of that gene.
و لكن لكل نسخة محتملة من ذلك الجين
So what does that mean?
إذن، ماذا يعني ذلك؟
That means that you can't give your gene to your doctor
إنه يعني أنك لا يمكنك إعطاء جينك لطبيبك
and ask him or her to look at it,
و تسأله او تسألها أن يلقوا نظرة عليه
say, to see if it has any mutations,
مثلا، لترى إن كان به أي طفرات
without permission of the patent holder.
دون أن تأخذ إذن حامل براءة الاختراع
It also means that the patent holder has the right to stop anyone
إنه يعني أيضا أن من حق حامل براءة الاختراع أن يمنع أي شخص
from using that gene in research or clinical testing.
من استخدام هذا الجين في البحوث أو الإختبارات العيادية
Allowing patent holders,
مما يسمح لحاملي براءة الإختراع
often private companies,
وهم في العادة شركات خاصة
to lock up stretches of the human genome was harming patients.
أن يغلقوا مجال الجينوم البشري مما يضر بالمرضى
Consider Abigail,
تأمل أبيجال
a 10-year-old with long QT syndrome,
ذلك الطفل ذو العاشرة و المصاب بمتلازمة long QT
a serious heart condition that, if left untreated,
و هو مرض قلبي خطير ، اذا لم يعالج،
can result in sudden death.
قد يسبب موت مفاجئ
The company that obtained a patent on two genes associated with this condition
طورت الشركة التي حصلت على براءتي اختراع في جينين مرتبطين بهذا المرض
developed a test to diagnose the syndrome.
اختباراً لتشخيص هذه المتلازمة
But then they went bankrupt and they never offered it.
و لكن بعد ذلك أعلنت الشركة إفلاسها و لم يقدموه أبداً
So another lab tried to offer the test,
لذلك، حاول معمل آخر أن يقدم الاختبار
but the company that held the patents threatened to sue the lab
لكن الشركة حاملة براءة الاختراع هددت أن تقاضي المعمل
for patent infringement.
بإنتهاك براءة الاختراع
So as a result,
و نتيجة لذلك
for 2 years, no test was available.
ظل الاختبار غير متاح لمدة عامين
During that time,
في أثناء ذلك
Abigail died of undiagnosed long QT.
مات أبيجال لعدم تشخيصه بمتلازمة long QT
Gene patents clearly were a problem and were harming patients.
من الواضح أن براءات الاختراع سببت مشكلة و كانت ذا ضرر للمرضى
But was there a way we could challenge them?
و لكن أكان هناك طريقة يمكننا بها تحديهم؟
Turns out that the Supreme Court
يظهر أن المحكمة العليا
has made clear through a long line of cases,
أوضحت خلال سلسلة طويلة من القضايا
that certain things are not patent eligible.
أن بعض الأشياء ليس من المسموح إعطاء براءة اختراع فيها
You can't patent products of nature --
لا يمكنك أن تسجل براءة اختراع في منتجات الطبيعة
the air, the water, minerals, elements of the periodic table.
كالهواء، الماء، الأملاح، عناصر الجدول الدوري
And you can't patent laws of nature --
و لا يمكنك التسجيل في قوانين الطبيعة
the law of gravity, E = mc2.
كقانون الجاذبية: الطاقة= الكتلة*سرعة الضوء ^2
These things are just too fundamental and must remain free to all
هذه أشياء أساسية و يجب أن تتاح للاستخدام من قبل الجميع
and reserved exclusively to none.
و ألا تحجز لأحد على وجه الخصوص
It seemed to us that DNA,
يبدو لنا أن ال DNA
the most fundamental structure of life,
و هو المكون الاساسي للحياة
that codes for the production of all of our proteins,
و الذي ينظم لإنتاج كل بروتيناتنا
is both a product of nature and a law of nature,
أحد منتجات الطبيعة و قوانين الطبيعة، كلاهما
regardless of whether it's in our bodies
بغض النظر إن كانت داخل أجسادنا
or sitting in the bottom of a test tube.
أو في قاع أنبوبة اختبار
As we delved into this issue,
بينما بحثنا في هذه المشكلة
we traveled all over the country to speak with many different experts --
سافرنا في كل أنحاء البلد لنتحدث مع مختلف الخبراء في مختلف المجالات
scientists, medical professionals, lawyers, patent lawyers.
علماء، اخصائيين طبيين، محامين، محامي براءات اختراع
Most of them agreed that we were right as a matter of policy,
وافق أغلبهم أننا على حق من الناحية السياسية
and, at least in theory, as a matter of law.
و من الناحية القانونية، على الأقل نظرياً
All of them thought
جميعهم اعتقدوا
our chances of winning a gene-patent challenge
أن احتمالية فوزنا بتحدي جينات براءة الاختراع
were about zero.
تقريباً صفر
Why is that?
لماذا ذلك؟
Well, the patent office had been issuing these patents
حسنا، مكتب براءة الاختراع سبب مشاكل فيما يخص براءات الاختراع تلك
for more than 20 years.
لأكثر من عشرين عاماً
There were literally thousands of patents on human genes.
كان هناك آلاف من براءات الإختراع في جينات الإنسان، حرفياً
The patent bar was deeply entrenched in the status quo,
اتخذ معادوا براءات الإختراع موقفاً معاديا من الوضع الراهن
the biotech industry had grown up around this practice,
تطورت صناعة التكنولوجيا الحيوية في ظل هذه الممارسة
and legislation to ban gene patents had been introduced
و تم تقديم تشريع لحظر حمل براءات اختراع في الجينات
year after year in Congress,
عاما بعد عام، و الكونغرس
and had gone absolutely nowhere.
لم يفعل شيئا ً على الإطلاق
So the bottom line:
لذلك، الحد الأدنى هو:
courts just weren't going to be willing to overturn these patents.
المحاكم لم ترد إسقاط براءات الإختراع
Now, neither Chris nor I were the type to shy away from a challenge,
الآن، لم أكن أنا و لا كريس من النوع الذي ينسحب من التحدي
and hearing, "Being right just isn't enough,"
و سماعنا إلى: " ليس كافياً أن تكون على صواب"
seemed all the more reason to take on this fight.
كان سبباً أن نقبل التحدي
So we set out to build our case.
لذلك، بدأنا التخطيط لبناء قضيتنا
Now, patent cases tend to be: Company A sues Company B
الآن، مالت قضايا براءات الإختراع لتكون على شكل: الشركة أ تقاضي الشركة ب
over some really narrow, obscure technical issue.
من أجل مشاكل ضئيلة، مبهمة، و فنية
We weren't really interested in that kind of case,
لم يثر إهتمامنا هذا النوع من المشاكل
and we thought this case was much bigger than that.
و اعتقدنا أن هذه القضية أكبر من ذلك
This was about scientific freedom, medical progress,
كان الأمر يتناول الحرية العلمية، التقدم الطبي،
the rights of patients.
و حقوق المرضى
So we decided we were going to develop a case
لذلك قررنا أن نطوّر قضية
that was not like your typical patent case --
ليست كقضية براءة اختراعك المعتادة
more like a civil rights case.
و لكن كقضية حقوق مدنية
We set out to identify a gene-patent holder
لقد خططنا لتعريف حامل براءة اختراع في الجينات
that was vigorously enforcing its patents
و الذي كان يستغل براءات اختراعه بشدة
and then to organize a broad coalition of plaintiffs and experts
و بعد ذلك تنظيم إئتلاف واسع من المدعين و الخبراء
that could tell the court
الذين يمكنهم إخبار المحكمة
about all the ways that these patents were harming patients and innovation.
عن كل الطرق التي تضر بها براءات الاختراع هؤلاء بالمرضي و الابتكار العلمي
We found the prime candidate to sue in Myriad Genetics,
كان المرشح الرئيسي للمقاضاة هي Myriad Genetics
a company that's based in Salt Lake City, Utah.
و هي شركة في مدينة سولت لاك، في يوتاه
Myriad held patents on two genes,
تحمل شركة Myriad برائتي اختراع في جينيت
the BRCA1 and the BRCA2 genes.
جين BRCA1 و جين BRCA2
Women with certain mutations along these genes
يعتبر النساء المصابون بطفرات على هذه الجينات
are considered to be at a significantly increased risk
في خطر مرتفع بشكل ملحوظ
of developing breast and ovarian cancer.
للإصابة بسرطان الثدي و سرطان المبيض
Myriad had used its patents to maintain
استخدمت Myriad براءة اختراعها لتبقي
a complete monopoly on BRCA testing in the United States.
احتكار كامل على استخدام BCRA في الولايات المتحدة
It had forced multiple labs that were offering BRCA testing to stop.
و هو ما اضطر معامل مختلفة لايقاف اختبارات ال BCRA
It charged a lot of money for its test --
مما كلف كثيراً من المال لإجراء الاختبار
over 3,000 dollars.
تزيد على 3000 دولار
It had stopped sharing its clinical data
لقد أوقفت الشركة مشاركة معلوماتها العيادية
with the international scientific community.
مع المجتمع العلمي العالمي
And perhaps worst of all,
و ربما كان الأسوأ على الإطلاق
for a period of several years,
لسنوات عديدة
Myriad refused to update its test to include additional mutations
أن رفضت Myriad أن تحدّث الاختبار ليشمل طفرات إضافية
that had been identified by a team of researchers in France.
التي تم اكتشافها من قبل فريق باحثين في فرنسا
It has been estimated that during that period,
من المقدر أن خلال تلك الفترة
for several years,
لعديد من السنوات
as many as 12 percent of women undergoing testing
12% من النساء اللواتي خضعن للاختبار
received the wrong answer --
حصلن على نتائج خاطئة
a negative test result that should have been positive.
نتائج اختبار سلبية كان من المفترض أن تكون إيجابية
This is Kathleen Maxian.
هنا كاثلين ماكسيام
Kathleen's sister Eileen developed breast cancer at age 40
إلين، شقيقة كاثلين، أصيبت بسرطان الثدي في عمر الأربعين
and she was tested by Myriad.
و تم اختبارها من قبل Myriad
The test was negative.
كانت النتيجة سلبية
The family was relieved.
ارتاحت العائلة
That meant that Eileen's cancer most likely didn't run in the family,
فهذا يعني أن سرطان إلين لا يسري في العائلة
and that other members of her family didn't need to be tested.
و أن أعضاء عائلتها الآخرين لا يحتاجون إلى الإختبار
But two years later,
لكن بعد عامين
Kathleen was diagnosed with advanced-stage ovarian cancer.
شخصت كاثلين بسرطان مبيض متقدم
It turned out that Kathleen's sister was among the 12 percent
يبدو أن شقيقة كاثلين كانت من ضمن ال 12%
who received a false-negative test result.
الذين تلقوا نتائج سلبية خاطئة
Had Eileen received the proper result,
فلو كانت إلين قد شخصت بشكل صحيح
Kathleen would have then been tested,
لكانت كاثلين قد خضعت للإختبار
and her ovarian cancer could have been prevented.
و لكان سرطان مبيضها قد أوقف
Once we settled on Myriad,
منذ استقرارنا على Myirad
we then had to form a coalition of plaintiffs and experts
كان علينا حين إذن تكوين تحالف من المدعين و الخبراء
that could illuminate these problems.
ممن يستطيعون إخراج تلك المشاكل إلى النور
We ended up with 20 highly committed plaintiffs:
انتهى الأمر بنا بالحصول على 20 مدعي ملتزمين بشكل كبير
genetic counselors,
مستشارين بعلم الوراثة
geneticists who had received cease and desist letters,
علماء وراثة ممن تلقوا جوابات فصل و إيقاف
advocacy organizations,
منظمات مؤيدة
four major scientific organizations that collectively represented
أربع مؤساسات بحثية مهمة، معاً مثلو
more than 150,000 scientists and medical professionals,
أكثر من 150،000 عالم و مختصين طبيين
and individual women who either couldn't afford Myriad's test,
و أفراد من النساء ممن لم يستطيعوا تحمل تكلفة اختبار Myriad
or who wanted to obtain a second opinion but could not,
أو أرادوا أن يحصلوا على رأي ثاني و لم يستطيعوا
as a result of the patents.
نتيجة لبراءات الاختراع
One of the major challenges we had in preparing the case
واحد من التحديات المهمة التي واجهتنا أثناء التحضير للقضية
was figuring out how best to communicate the science.
هو اكتشاف كم من الجيد التواصل مع العلم
So in order to argue that what Myriad did was not an invention,
لذلك ، من أجل مناقشة أن ما فعلته Myriad لم يكن اختراعا
and that isolated BRCA genes were products of nature,
و أن ال BCRA جين من منتجات الطبيعة
we had to explain a couple of basic concepts, like:
كان علينا شرح بعض المفاهيم الأساسية
What's a gene? What's DNA?
ما هو ال gene ؟ ما هو ال DNA؟
How is DNA isolated, and why isn't that an invention?
كيف يتم عزل ال DNA؟ و كيف لا يكون هذا اختراعا؟
We spent hours and hours with our plaintiffs and experts,
لقد قضينا ساعات و ساعات مع المدعين و الخبراء
trying to come up with ways of explaining these concepts
محاولين الإتيان بطرق لشرح هذه المفاهيم
simply yet accurately.
بشكل مبسط و دقيق
And we ended up relying heavily on the use of metaphors,
و انتهى بنا الأمر معتمدين بشكل كبير على التعبيرات المجازية
like gold.
مثل الذهب
So isolating DNA --
لذلك. عزل ال DNA
it's like extracting gold from a mountain
مثل استخلاص الذهب من جبل
or taking it out of a stream bed.
أو إخراجه من قاع نهر
You might be able to patent the process for mining the gold,
يمكنك أن تحصل على براءة اختراع في كيفية تعدين الذهب
but you can't patent the gold itself.
لكن ليس براءة اختراع الذهب نفسه
It might've taken a lot of hard work and effort
ربما يأخذ الأمر كثيرا من الجهد و العمل الجاد
to dig the gold out of the mountain;
لكي تستخرج الذهب من الجبل
you still can't patent it, it's still gold.
لكن لا زال لا يمكن أن تحصل على براءة إختراع في ذهب. إنه ما زال ذهب.
And the gold, once it's extracted,
و بمجرد استخراج الذهب
can clearly be used for all sorts of things
يمكن استخدامه في كثير من الاشياء
that it couldn't be used for when it was in the mountain;
التي لم يمكن من الممكن تنفيذها حين كان الذهب في الجبل
you can make jewelry out of it for example --
فمثلا، يمكنك استخدامه في صناعة المجوهرات
still can't patent the gold, it's still gold.
ما زال لا يمكنك الحصول على براءة اختراع في الذهب. فهو مازال ذهبا
So now it's 2009, and we're ready to file our case.
الآن، نحن في عام 2009 ، و مستعدون لنشر قضيتنا
We filed in federal court in the Southern District of New York,
قمنا بنشرها في المحكمة الفيدرالية، في المنطقة الشمالية من نيويورك،
and the case was randomly assigned to Judge Robert Sweet.
و بشكل عشوائي، تم تكليف القاضي روبرت سويت بتناول القضية
In March 2010, Judge Sweet issued his opinion --
في مارس 2010، أصدر القاضي سويت رأيه
152 pages --
152 صفحة
and a complete victory for our side.
و نصر كامل لصالح قضيتنا
In reading the opinion,
بينما نقرأ رأيه
we could not get over how eloquently he described the science in the case.
لم نستطع أن نتجاوز كيف وصف العلم في القضية بشكل بليغ
I mean, our brief -- it was pretty good,
أعني. رأينا كان جيدا
but not this good.
لكن ليس إلى هذه الدرجة
How did he develop such a deep understanding of this issue
كيف استطاع ان يطور هذا الفهم العميق للقضية
in such a short time?
في هذا الوقت القصير؟
We just could not comprehend how this had happened.
لم نستطع أن نفهم كيف حدث ذلك
So it turned out,
لذلك، يبدو أن
Judge Sweet's clerk working for him at the time,
موظفا لدى القاضي سويت
was not just a lawyer --
لم يكن مجرد محامي
he was a scientist.
لقد كان عالما
He was not just a scientist --
لم يكن مجرد عالم
he had a PhD in molecular biology.
لقد حصل على الدكتوراه في البيولوجيا الجزيئية
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
What an incredible stroke of luck!
ما أروع ضربة الحظ هذه!
Myriad then appealed
بعد ذلك استأنفت Myriad
to the US Court of Appeals for the Federal Circuit.
في محكمة استئناف الولايات المتحدة للدائرة الفيدرالية
And here things got really interesting.
و هنا أصبحت الأمور حقا أكثر إثارة
First, in a pivotal moment of this case,
أولا، في نقطة محورية من هذه القضية،
the US government switched sides.
بدلت حكومة الولايات المتحدة الأدوار
So in the district court the government submitted a brief on Myriad's side.
لذلك في محكمة المنطقة، سلمت الحكومة خطابا مختصرا لصالح Myriad
But now in direct opposition to its own patent office,
و لكن الآن، و في تضاد مباشر لمكتب براءات الاختراع الخاص بها
the US government files a brief that states that is has
أصدرت الحكومة خطابا ينص على
reconsidered this issue in light of the district court's opinion,
إعادة النظر في تلك القضية في ظل رأي محكمة المنطقة
and has concluded that isolated DNA is not patent eligible.
و استنتجوا أن ال DNA المعزول ليس براءة اختراع
This was a really big deal,
كان هذا أمرا كبيرا حقا
totally unexpected.
و غير متوقع بشكل كامل
The Court of Appeals for the Federal Circuit
استمعت محكمة الاستئناف للدائرة الفيدرالية
hears all patent cases,
إلى كل قضايا براءات الإختراع
and it has a reputation for being very, very pro-patent.
و قد سمع عنها انها مؤيدة لبراءات الإختراع
So even with this remarkable development,
لذلك، بالرغم من هذا التقدم الملحوظ
we expected to lose.
توقعنا أن نخسر
And we did.
و قد حدث
Sort of.
نوعا ما
Ends up split decision, 2 to 1.
انتهى الأمر بانقسام في الرأي، اثنين إلى واحد
But the two judges who ruled against us,
و لكن القاضيين اللذين حكما ضدنا
did so for completely different reasons.
قاما بذلك لأسباب مختلفة تماما
The first one, Judge Lourie,
القاضي الاولي يدعي لوري
made up his own novel, biological theory --
اعتمد على نظرية بيولوجية
totally wrong.
خاطئة تماما
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
He decided Myriad had created a new chemical --
لقد قرر أن Myriad صنعت مادة كيميائية جديدة
made absolutely no sense.
الأمر لا يعقل على الاطلاق
Myriad didn't even argue this, so it came out of the blue.
لم تجادل Myriads, لقد خرجت من الظلام
The other, Judge Moore,
القاضي الآخر، موري
said she basically agreed with us that isolated DNA is a product of nature.
قالت أنها بشكل أساسي متفقة معنا أن ال DNA المعزول هو ناتج من الطبيعة
But she's like, "I don't want to shake up the biotech industry."
و لكنها كانت تظن:" أنا لا أريد أن أزعزع صناعة التكنولوجيا الحيوية"
The third, Judge Bryson,
القاضي الثالث، بريسون
agreed with us.
اتفق معنا
So now we sought review by the Supreme Court.
لذلك الآن قمنا بإلتماس في المحكمة العليا
And when you petition the Supreme Court,
و عندما تقدم إلتماساَ في المحكمة العليا
you have to present a question that you want the Court to answer.
عليك أن تقدم سؤالا للمحكمة كي تجيبه
Usually these questions take the form of a super-long paragraph,
عادة ما تأخذ شكل فقرة طويلة
like a whole page long with lots and lots of clauses,
مثل صفحة كاملة مليئة بالكثير من البنود
"wherein this" and "therefore that."
"بما أن" و "إذن"
We submitted perhaps the shortest question presented ever.
لقد قدمنا أقصر سؤال تم تقديمه تقريباَ
Four words:
أربع كلمات:
Are human genes patentable?
أيحق لأحد أن يأخذ براءة اختراع في الجينات؟
Now when Chris first asked me what I thought of these words,
الآن، عندما سألني كريس عن رأيي في هذه الكلمات
I said, "Well, I don't know.
قلت:"حسنا، لا أعرف.
I think you have to say, 'Is isolated DNA patentable?'"
ربما عليك أن تقول: هل يحق لأحد أن يأخذ براءة اختراع في الجينات؟"
"Nope.
"كلا.
I want the justices to have the very same reaction that I had
أريد للقضاة أن يتخذوا نفس رد فعلي
when you brought this issue to me seven years ago."
عندما طرحت عليّ تلك المشكلة من سبع سنوات"
Well, I certainly couldn't argue with that.
حسنا، أنا حقا لم أستطع أن أجادله في ذلك
The Supreme Court only hears about one percent
تستمتع المحكمة العليا ل 1% فقط
of the cases that it receives,
من القضايا المقدمة إليها
and it agreed to hear ours.
و وافقت على الإستماع إلينا
The day of the oral argument arrives, and it was really, really exciting --
جاء يوم المرافعة الشفهية، و الذي كان مثيراً جدا جدا
long line of people outside,
صف طويل من الناس بالخارج
people had been standing in line since 2:30 in the morning
واقفين في الصف من 2:30 صباحا
to try to get into the courthouse.
ليحاولوا دخول قاعة المحكمة
Two breast cancer organizations,
منظمتين لسرطان الثدي
Breast Cancer Action and FORCE,
Breast Cancer Action و FORCE
had organized a demonstration on the courthouse steps.
نظموا مظاهرة على أعتاب المحكمة
Chris and I sat quietly in the hallway,
بينما جلست أنا و كريس صامتين في المدخل
moments before he was to walk in and argue
قبل لحظات من دخوله لمناقشة
the most important case of his career.
أهم قضية في حياته المهنية
I was clearly more nervous than he was.
كان من الواضح كم كنت متوترة أكثر منه
But any remaining panic subsided as I walked into the courtroom
و لكني هدأت حين دخلت إلى قاعة المحكمة
and looked around at a sea of friendly faces:
و نظرت إلى هذا الكم من الوجوه المبتسمة
our individual women clients
عميلاتنا من السيدات
who had shared their deeply personal stories,
ممن شاركوا بقصصهم الشخصية جدا
the geneticists who had taken huge chunks of time out of their busy careers
علماء الوراثة الذين ضحوا بكثير من أوقاتهم المهنية
to dedicate themselves to this fight
ليكرسوا أنفسهم لهذه القضية
and representatives from a diverse array
و مجموعة متنوعة من الممثلين
of medical, patient advocacy,
الأطباء، هيئة الدفاع عن المرضى
environmental and religious organizations,
منظمات دينية و بيئية
who had submitted friend of the court briefs in the case.
قدموا مذكرة إلى المحكمة في القضية
Also in the room were three leaders of the Human Genome Project,
و أيضا، كان في القاعة ثلاث قادة من مشروع الجينوم البشري
including the co-discoverer of DNA himself,
من بينهم واحد ممن ساهموا في اكتشاف ال DNA
James Watson,
جايمس واتسون
who had submitted a brief to the court,
و الذي قدم مذكرة إلى المحكمة
where he referred to gene patenting as "lunacy."
أشار فيها إلي منح براءة اختراع في الجينات ب"الحماقة"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
The diversity of the communities represented in this room
تنوع الجماعات الممثلة في القاعة
and the contributions each had made to make this day a reality
و مساهمات كل منهم جعلت من هذا اليوم واقعاً
spoke volumes to what was at stake.
بعد أن كان على المحك
The argument itself was riveting.
المرافعة ذاتها كانت مثيرة للإعجاب
Chris argued brilliantly.
رافع كريس بمنتهى الذكاء
But for me,
و لكن بالنسبة إليّ
the most thrilling aspect was watching the Supreme Court justices grapple
كان أكثر جانب مثير هو تعامل القضاة
with isolated DNA,
مع ال DNA المعزول
through a series of colorful analogies and feisty exchanges,
رغم سلسلة التشبيهات الساخنة و التبديلات المشاكسة
very much the same way as our legal team had done
بنفس طريقة التي تعامل بها فريقنا القانوني
for the past seven years.
خلال السبع سنوات المنصرمة
Justice Kagan likened isolating DNA
شبه القاضي كاجين ال DNA المعزول
to extracting a medicinal plant from the Amazon.
باستخراج نبات طبي من نهر الأمازون
Justice Roberts distinguished it from carving a baseball bat from a tree.
بينما شبهه القاضي روبرتز بنحت مضرب بيسبول في شجرة
And in one of my absolutely favorite moments,
و في احدي لحظاتي المفضلة
Justice Sotomayor proclaimed isolated DNA to be "just nature sitting there."
أعلن القاضي سوتومايور أن الDNA المعزول "ليس إلا طبيعة جالسة أمامنا"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
We felt pretty confident leaving the courtroom that day,
شعرنا بثقة كبيرة أثناء مغادرتنا قاعة المحكمة في ذلك اليوم
but I could never have anticipated the outcome:
لكني لم أستطع أبداّ أن أتوقع النتيجة:
nine to zero.
تسعة إلى صفر
"A naturally occurring DNA segment is a product of nature,
"جزء من ال DNA المكون بشكل طبيعي هو أحد نواتج الطبيعة"
and not patent-eligible merely because it has been isolated.
و كونه معزول ببساطة لا يجعله مؤهلاً للحصول على براءة اختراع فيه
And furthermore,
و علاوة على ذلك
Myriad did not create anything."
Myriad لم تصنع شيئاً
Within 24 hours of the decision,
خلال 24 ساعة من القرار
five labs had announced
أعلنت 6 معامل
that they would begin to offer testing for the BRCA genes.
انهم سيبدأون بتقديم اختبارلجينات الBRCA
Some of them promised to offer the tests at a lower price than Myriad's.
و وعد بعضهم بتقديم الاختبار بسعر أقل من ذلك الذي كانت تقدمه Myriad
Some promised to provide a more comprehensive test
وعد البعض بتقديم اختبار أكثر شمولاً
than the one Myriad was offering.
من ذلك الذي كانت تقدمه Myriad
But of course the decision goes far beyond Myriad.
و لكن بالطبع، القرار أكبر بكثير من Myriad
It ends a 25-year practice of allowing patents on human genes
لقد انهى 25 عاماً من منح براءات الاختراع في الجينات البشرية
in the United States.
في الولايات المتحدة
It clears a significant barrier to biomedical discovery and innovation.
و محت حاجزا رئيسيا في طريق الإكتشافات و الإبتكارات البيوكيميائية
And it helps to ensure that patients like Abigail, Kathleen and Eileen
و ساعدت على تأكيد ان مرضي كأبيجال، كاثلين و إلين
have access to the tests that they need.
لديهم حق الحصول على الاختبارات التي احتاجوها
A few weeks after the court issued its decision,
بعد أسابيع قليلة من إعلان المحكمة عن قرارها
I received a small package in the mail.
تلقيت طرداً في البريد
It was from Bob Cook-Deegan,
من بوب كوك ديجان
a professor at Duke University
أستاذ في جامعة دوك
and one the very first people Chris and I went to visit
و واحد من أوائل من زرتهم أنا و كريس
when we started to consider whether to bring this case.
عندما بدأنا مناقشة هذه القضية
I opened it up to find a small stuffed animal.
فتحتها، و وجدت حيوانا صغيرا محنطا
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
We took a big risk in taking this case.
لقد أخذنا مخاطرة كبيرة حين قبلنا تلك القضية
Part of what gave us the courage to take that risk
و مما دفعنا إلى أخذ تلك المخاطرة
was knowing that we were doing the right thing.
علمنا أننا كنا على حق
The process took nearly eight years from the start to finish,
أخذ الأمر حوالي 8 سنوات من البداية للنهاية
with many twists and turns along the way.
مع الكثير من التقلبات و الانعطافات في الطريق
A little luck certainly helped,
قليل من الحظ ساعدنا بالطبع
but it was the communities that we bridged,
لكن المجموعات التي بنيناها
the alliances that we created,
و التحالفات التي كونّاها
that made pigs fly.
هي صاحبة الفضل
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)